More time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism,
to see and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young
host this live Colin show, focused on enchantment in creation.
union of the scene and unseen as made by God.
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Good evening, giant killers and dragon slayers.
You are listening to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
And my co-host, Father Stephen D'Young, is with me
from Lafayette, Louisiana.
And I'm Father Andrew Stephen Daymak in Emeas, Pennsylvania.
And we are live, unlike two weeks ago,
where we were live, but not live.
But we saw you. It was weird.
I don't know. I mean it's
having met so many of you now. Did it make it weird? What do you think, Father?
Yes.
Yeah. But we're gonna, you know, soldier on. So if you are listening to us live, you can call us tonight.
855-237-2346, talk to us. We're gonna get to your calls in the second half of the show. And Elijah is gonna be taking your calls.
So he's sitting in for Mattress Goodtry to be tonight.
And listen, listen folks. I just found out this is a kid.
right
This is an on Janu. You have certain playful and suciance if you will.
Don't be calling in with your sailor talk and teaching him words he's never heard before, okay?
Keep it cool. Dolly noted.
You know, the sad thing is Elijah, like he would be really uncouth for him to just like break in
and say, hey now, I've heard some words. So he won't.
Uh...
Alright, now it's time to sell some coffee.
So, the Lotus Spirit's podcast is brought to you by our listeners with help from
Lore Coffee Roasters.
Lore Coffee Roasters is a specialty coffee company owned and operated by two Orthodox
Christian families working to glorify God in all things.
The Lore team is focused on sourcing and roasting the highest quality coffee from all over
the earth, even Venowatu, or maybe not, and having a deliver to your door in a seamless
experience.
built-in subscription platform on their website making it easy.
you to choose your coffee, how much of it you would like, how often you want it delivered,
they are also equipped to provide whole sailing solutions for select partnerships. Help
support Lord of Spirits by choosing coffee from lower coffee roasters and Orthodox specialty
coffee company and be a part of the story behind good coffee. You can view their coffee library
and subscription plans at lore roasters.com. You can follow them on Instagram and Facebook
at Laura Coffee Roasters, and hey there's a discount. 10% off your f-
first order, you can use the discount code, LOS10, LOS10. So get your coffee. I've had some.
It's good. Like it would drink again. So yes. I have a little advertisement of my own,
everybody. Shameless self promotion. Shameless self promotion. I mean, you did say that I get
to be the Stanley of online orthodoxy. So, Excel's here.
Right, so if you've been living under a rock, which is one of my favorite expressions,
the idea that someone who doesn't know what's going on lives under a rock.
If you've been living under a rock, you may not be aware that there is a new book written
by your humble servant with a foreword by the very Reverend Dr. Ogre sitting on the other
end of the line for me.
And it is titled simply The Lord of Spirits and Orthodox Christian framework for the unseen
world and spiritual warfare.
It is a distillation of much of the podcast, but also a lot of new material that even super,
super ravenous Lord of Spirits listeners have never encountered before, at least not from us.
So get yourself a copy, store.inchandfaith.com. They're apparently selling like hotcakes, which
apparently hotcakes sell really well, with thus lending us that metaphor. I've never bought that
that I can recall is I hop stock doing that well?
I do not know.
I've not been to the International House of Pancakes in some time.
And is the, I feel like there was an inter-marketing error with this book though.
Oh, because I mean, I think the big selling point was like the first three pages.
And you gave those away for free in the sample.
It's true.
People can read your forward for free in the sample and the introduction and chapter one.
Yeah.
And it's like, you know, you got the best part.
So I know.
Well, you know, I mean this podcast is free.
They don't serve people who deserve first.
It is one of the best forwards I have ever read this week.
You read a lot of forwards.
I am one of those people who like, okay, you know, like this is a really boring introduction
on this major academic work, but I will read it because it is in the book.
So everyone should be a completist.
Unless...
your Jamie Bennett. He never finishes books he doesn't like.
Does yeah, does see I feel I don't finish books. I don't like. It's really
an excuse for the stack of unread books that he and many other people have.
He's just not willing to man up and admit it.
Call us Jamie Bennett. Let us know what's going on.
Turn up your loins and admit that you just haven't read all your books.
Let's get your wife up with the phone. I want to hear what she thinks about this
big stack of books that you've got like
around. Partly red. So, all right. Well, tonight we're heading back into deep waters discussing
questions of interpretation of the scriptures and the church fathers. What do these texts mean?
How do they get applied? And is our thinking on this question usually kind of modernist?
And if so, how do we get out of that way of thinking? So, turns out that the answers to these,
and so many other questions starts in jazz.
chapter one, which makes Shocker, right? Like we don't we don't ever do that.
Well, yeah, well, you're bearing the lead here. You're making it sound like we're starting with
the creation of the world, but we're actually going to go back before that. Yeah, it's true. It's
right. So Genesis zero. Yeah, we're going as far back as you could go back. There's no more back
after that before that back was not in existence yet, which we can say words like nothing, but you
You can't.
think of nothing.
Yes.
Yes, because when you think of nothing,
you're thinking of something.
Like in the never ending story.
I mean, the nothing was definitely something
that you sought from.
You're traumatizing people.
You're traumatizing people about the horse.
You don't need to know that.
You know, I watched that movie again
like a couple of years ago.
It did not hold up for me.
I don't know.
I felt really bad about that too,
because it had this wonderful little space
And my...
childhood memory and then I kind of killed it by watching it again.
Yeah. Yeah.
People should post more courtesy lists of things to not revisit.
Mm. Right.
Like I'll put out the list super friends and Thundercats like.
Ooh. Yeah.
I never. Yeah.
I have fun back there.
Don't go there, man.
Now that you've said that I think I won't.
Yeah.
I will occasionally I do say things like Thundercats hoe.
I mean, every so often just in my life, but yeah.
Yeah, I'm not watching the show.
Yeah, yeah. Usually you're throwing gang signs when you yell that too, which is
your part. But we won't discuss your lifestyle outside of the show.
Thank you. Personal life should remain your own on the mean streets of a mass.
So yeah, we're starting at the beginning of beginnings, right? And also fair warning,
Uh
we're going kind of deep in the show.
So we're kind of going into the deep end.
We do that every once in a while.
It's been a minute since we did that,
but we're doing it again.
So everyone's warned.
But we're starting out by sort of reviewing
a little bit of stuff that we've talked about in the past.
This episode as a whole,
we're going to be like picking up
information, we're picking up some threads from some past episodes and kind of weaving
them together to look at, bring some things together and look at some things from a certain
perspective.
So, we're going to start out with some comfortable review before we dive into the
deep end.
Siddling kids, these are all parts of the book you've read before.
Yeah.
So, part of play the hit here for a minute before we get into the new material.
you
So, one of the probably the overriding theme tonight that we're going to be talking about,
because we're talking tonight about meaning.
And meaning is inextricably related to order.
And so order as in patterns, as in systems, as in structure.
Right. You kind of can't have meaning without it, right? Chaos does not have meaning sort of by definition. Yeah.
Yeah. Gibberish is not meaningful until you like. Nothing. Some kind of order on it. Yeah. Nothingness cannot be put in order, right? Because it's nothing.
And if it gets put in order, it becomes something, right? And that's how we've talked about creation in the past.
that the way Genesis
one presents God's creation of the world is in terms of this twofold pattern. He's dealing
with the two problems of the earth at the beginning of his creative act being formless and
empty. And so on the first three days he puts, he has most an order, on the second set
of three days he fills it with life. And that these two things are commensurate.
things being put in order is what allows life to flourish.
So this is not an order at the expense of life, like a kind of tyranny,
but this is also not life grown out of control and turning into chaos.
These two mutually go together.
So we've we've talked about this a lot in creation, but the question we maybe
haven't asked and therefore haven't answered is what?
is order. You just sort of assume people have some idea of what that is. Which we do, but
maybe let's look underneath that. Yeah. Yeah. And what would the definition of order be?
How do we define it? How do we understand what that term means? And you can't,
Sometimes when you've got something that's in kind of a polarity, right?
or a distinction. So we've got order order is as opposed to chaos. Right. You have order on one side,
you have chaos on the other, right? Being and non-being, right. But you can't define order in terms of a lack of chaos.
Right. Right. Right. Which is sometimes how we're attempted to do things. Right. You define darkness as an
absent of light, absence of light, right?
But
you can't define light then as an absence of darkness.
No. Or at least if you try to, it makes it clear that you don't know what either term
means. Right? You're just describing that as the lack of the other. Right?
Although when I was a stage-hand, we used to tell people some performers that would come
to our theater that we had spray cans of light be gone because they would complain about
light being on a particular part of the set or something like that.
Can you light this?
That's two inches from that and then not that?
Like, oh, let me just go get my can of light because.
We know there is that black paint now.
Yes.
It sucks all light in it absorbs all light.
One time we were actually asked to light a dancer but not the floor that she was standing
on.
And we're like, okay, we're going to have to have a meeting.
Ha ha ha ha.
Yeah, good time.
So that dog don't hunt, right?
Yes, yes.
Because what chaos is definitionally, right, because chaos, as we've talked about it,
is non-being, right?
Non-being, the very structure of the word, it's a negation of being, right?
So of the two terms order in chaos, chaos is the one that's an negation.
This is an absent.
absence of order, not vice versa.
Right. And I know this already was a hard concept.
Right. Because we still get questions about this from people who listen to the old order and chaos
episode, where we talked about God being presented as creating things out of primordial chaos.
And we get the question, well, who made the primordial chaos?
Yeah, because they they would probably think of the primordial chaos as being like the nothing in
in the never-ending story, like it's this big,
roiling cloud of darkness, you know?
Yeah, it's a thing. Right. And the whole point of it is that it's no thing. If someone created it,
it wouldn't be chaos that you are. Yeah. Right. And that question is sort of like asking when
someone says God created ex nihilo out of nothing, you're saying, yeah, well, who created the nothing?
Right. Nothing created the nothing. It's nothing. It's not a thing. Right. Yeah.
So I know that's already hard. Right. But chaos is just a negation.
order. So then what is this order that we're talking about? Let me say that God ordered the creation.
There are different ways that this can and has been understood.
So for example, some folks, Plato's one of them, will posit that there is some kind of order
some kind of pattern
That is external to God meaning it's not God himself, right?
And that imposes some kind of necessity on God
As he creates. Yeah, he has to
Obey it follow it. Yeah follow that pattern follow that right
Plato in the Tameyus right the Demiurge right
Hey.
Chris.
creates everything after the pattern of the eternal forms.
Right.
So there, the eternal forms are external to the creator for Plato
and the creators beholden to them.
Right.
Now, there's obviously a big problem in terms of that
with the Christian God.
Yeah, because God doesn't have to obey anything.
Right.
There are certain people out of the West
with three initials who don't follow.
that. Right. You say that God has to obey the laws of logic, but those people are
frackedly wrong. So you'd expect them to be wrong about this too. Um, that is, so that
is not the Christian God, right? So that's a nope. Right. The idea that there's some
external pattern or order or system of justice that God has to obey. Yeah. Because again,
if there's something above God, then you should worship that. Yeah. Then that's actually
God. Yeah.
So there's another way of looking at this, where this order or this pattern is something
that is not God Himself that is separate from God, right?
But is not above Him or does not impose any necessity on Him, meaning it's contingent.
So either God created this pattern and then created everything else according to the pattern.
right? Or this patterns is some other way subsidiary or God could have used a completely different
pattern if he wanted to. Yeah, it's sort of God as a divine architect who makes blueprints
beforehand. Right. And which he could have made in whatever way. And this by the way, Tolkien
fans is the model that's presented at the beginning of the summer early on the Analinda.
I'm the lindel, I knew lindel a easy for me to say where, you know,
there's the music, which is basically the Boo print for creation and then creation follows
from that. But that's not what's in the scripture. It's not the Christian tradition.
The rest cool is that is in Tolkien. But that's not what, that's not what we see.
But this is a, this is a different view, right? Yeah. So in order to get at the biblical
We have to go to one passage that I know is always at the forefront.
of everyone's mind. That's Proverbs chapter 8 verses 22 through 31. Yeah, you probably don't
even have to read it. You probably have all of them. Proverbs is one of those books that I think
really gets ignored by a lot of Christians. But if you just at least read it or listen to it and
try to do some of what it says. That's kind of, I mean, it is a blueprint for good Christian.
living. Yeah. And if you yes, and this passage in particular, if you're not aware of this passage,
you will not understand any church father ever. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Quite literally. Okay. So
Proverbs 8 verses 22 through 31, the speaker here is identified as wisdom. So starting with verse 22,
the Lord fathered me at the beginning of his work. The first of his acts of old ages ago,
I was set up at the first before the beginning of the earth.
When there were no depths I was brought forth.
When there were no springs abounding with water.
Before the mountains had been shaved, before the hills I was brought forth, before he had
made the earth with its fields or the first of the dust of the world.
When he established the heavens I was there.
When he drew a circle in the face of the deep, when he made firm the skies above, when
he established the fountains of the deep, when he assigned to the sea its limit so that
the waters might not transgress this command.
when he marked out the foundations of the earth, then I was beside him, like a master
workman. And I was daily his delight rejoicing before him always rejoicing in his inhabited
world and delighting in the children of man. That's a cool passage. But it's in Proverbs,
which no one reads people don't even know what's there. You know, we're busy talking about
the ideal woman in chapter 31.
That's right.
Yes, so yeah.
First people know.
So this is, this is,
let me go ahead and break a few hearts.
Cause I know that despite my best efforts,
there's some people out there the audience
who are still clinging to this whole
some version of the Greek Old Testament
is the canonical Old Testament.
So the Greek actually completely
bolixes this text in a heretical way.
Yeah. Yeah.
the first verse, well, first one, too. Yeah. Yeah. So this, yeah, you got to deal with
that. Yeah, you're going to be a Greek OT supremacist. Yeah. So here's, here's what the, here's
what the Greek says. It says, the Lord created me at the beginning of his work. That's what
it says. The Lord created me. But what does the Hebrew say? Rather than fathered me. Yeah,
Fathered or be got be got is just a good old Older English word for that I was
brought forth is again, it's the Hebrew verb, yellow, it's giving birth to.
Yeah. And so here's the thing. I mean, you can try to understand the Greek in an orthodox way,
but it's a big stretch, which, you know, the Aryans knew that. And so they said, see, see,
he's a creed at being there's a line in the creed, begotten not made that is specifically
correcting this. Right, right.
So it's just not the best translation there in in the sub two. Yeah, and we can understand why in the third century BC
rabbis and Alexandria
dealing with a gentile audience who's gonna be reading this would be uncomfortable with the idea of talking about God
begetting fathering giving birth
Yeah, and so they kind of shrank away from it and changed it
But yeah.
The original was important, right?
And you notice in the passage, right, all the language, right about mountains and springs
in the depths and the limit of the sea, this is all the language of the first three days
of creation.
Yeah.
Where God, you know, brings order to the chaotic world, creates the structure.
And so here...
in Proverbs 8, 22 through 31, the pattern by which through which after which God creates
the cosmos is His wisdom.
His wisdom which is here, personified.
So this right here, this is how Trinitarianism works, right?
original version, that various versions of
around today. Right? So we're talking about Yahweh. That's the Lord at the beginning. Right?
Talk about God, capital G, God the Father, right? Because he's fathering. Right?
God is never without His wisdom. Right? There wasn't a time when God was foolish and then He acquired
wisdom. Right. Right. Right. Yeah. This is basic. Right. God is never
without his wisdom. Yeah, here we can see that his wisdom is distinguished from him, right?
Could be said to be with him, to be alongside him, right? To be working with him, to be his
delight, et cetera. Right? But his wisdom is not external to him. It is not as if he has
There's no wisdom and he has to consult with wisdom as this.
being right it is his wisdom right right it's his wisdom yeah this is the this is the biblical
Trinitarian theology that the later more philosophical formulations are
protecting frankly yeah and explaining in green right and the relationship between the two
right
these two personal beings who are not external to each other.
Right. They're described as one of beginning.
Yet begotten not made. Right. And one is begotten from the other and not vice versa.
Yes, so there's a derivative relationship. Right.
Right, between one and the other.
That derivative relationship is
why there's still one God, because there's one first principle. And the sun, the one who's
given birth to, is the image of the one who gave birth. Remember this is how father and
son works. We've talked about this a lot of times, biblically. They're the same thing.
not different things. The Sun is the exact image of the Father.
So, when the Hebrew Scriptures, when the Old Testament describes this pattern, this
order in which and through which God creates everything, it describes it as this divine
person who has begotten of God.
Before anything is created.
But it has to be begotten timelessly because again, God is never without His wisdom.
Yeah, so eternal beginning is right here in Proverbs 8.
Yeah.
And who is the exact image of God?
And the original readers of this,
Make sure your lights, second-templed Jewish people understood.
this. And they interpreted Genesis 1 in light of this, in light of this understanding.
And so when you go back to Genesis 1 with this in mind, what do you find? Well, God creates
by speaking in Genesis 1. We kind of take that for granted. But God doesn't take his hand
and then, you know,
things out and build up mountains, right? He speaks, right? And so it's his word that is the mediating factor between God and the creation.
And so an even more common name for God's wisdom in this context becomes the logos, right? The logos of creation, right? The pattern of creation, but the logos again,
like Wisdom in Proverbs is a person.
Right, a person who has always been with God.
God has never been mindless, right?
He's never been without his logos, right?
He's never been speechless.
He's never been without his logos.
And so, his logos is not external to him, is not contingent.
Right?
This isn't a contingent being.
God's logos couldn't be a different logos
right? God's wisdom couldn't be a different wisdom. Because this is an eternal timeless person.
Who's beginning with timeless? I couldn't have a different logos.
And you find this very clearly, right? First century BC,
Philo of Alexandria, you find this very clearly, this fully developed line of interpretation.
And it's right there for say, Satan.
John to pick up at the beginning of his gospel.
Yeah, I mean, yeah, Saint John, you know, John chapter one is basically recapitulation
of all this.
Right.
And the state was at that point, right?
This was the understanding derived from and of the Hebrew scriptures previous to that
point.
So now we need to put a pin there for a second.
There's gonna be a lot of pins in this.
episode people. Yeah, this is the
Charlie Day wall of of Lord of
Spirit episodes. So we're going
to pin that for just a second. We've
got a couple more threads to pick
up from another old episode. And
that's actually the episode we did
about God's body. Those are early
episodes, I think, right? Yes, we're
digging in the crates. We're setting
the wave out.
Right. So in that episode, right, we talked about how man is made in the image of God. We've talked about that a lot.
Right.
But man be made in the image of God. But we specifically in that case talked about the fact that the language that often gets read, especially in the
the visual testament, the revival, as being anthropomorphic language.
language that talks about the eyes of God, right, or the ears of God, or God being long of
nose, right? That tends to be read by modern people as anthropomorphism. Yeah, that God is being
made to look like a man. Right. That humans are sort of imagining God in some kind of human form or
mold. Right. But what you talked about there is that for the
the scripture is the opposite is true.
Right.
And this is the key to understanding man being made in the image of God,
that humanity is actually feel more thick.
Yeah. And I mean, one of the ways that this gets illustrated iconographically is
if you ever see an Orthodox icon of the creation of Adam,
number one, the one doing the creating is, is Jesus.
You know, it's not some faceless Jack Chick-Godd on his throne.
around.
It's Jesus. It's clearly Jesus, right? He's creating Adam and Adam is made to look like
Him. Adam looks like Jesus as the creation is happening, or that gets expressed in icons
in that particular way.
Right.
So when we talk about God's eyes, we're talking about the power of sight, we're talking
about that in the truest sense. And then human sight is a derivative, right? Type of
that power.
Yeah, God's powers are not just big versions of...
human powers, human powers are little versions of God powers.
Small diminished. Yeah. Yeah. Right.
Right. And so God creates essentially little potential small G
gods. Right.
This is the front side of what we call theosis. Right.
And the way they move
toward that goal is intended to be by imaging God, meaning by continuing the work of God in creation,
continuing to set creation in order, continuing to fill it with life. We've talked about this
before. And so, humanity, God is continuing that work and humanity participates in it,
right, participates in God and His grace allows that.
to be mediated through humanity and that is transformative to humanity, shaping humanity further
in the in the likeness of God. And so we've talked about how in paradise when man and woman are
created, they're created with the intent that the two of them would leave the garden because the
The garden is not the whole of the earth.
leave the garden taking paradise with them and spread out and turn the world into paradise
by putting it in order and filling it with life, filling the earthen subduing it.
Edenization as it were of the world.
Right.
And to do this is to humanize the world, right?
Because that action is mediated through humanity.
even though humanity disobeyed.
the relationship between humanity and the rest of creation is such that the world is humanized
anyway. So Adam gets told, cursed is the ground because of you. Yeah, no matter what we do,
we're going to affect the world. Right. And so if we're not doing what we've been called to do by
God, then our sin, our wickedness is going to dispoil, taint.
twist, right, the rest of creation around us.
Right.
Because this humanization is unavoidable, but that's because of the relationship of humanity
to the rest of creation.
And so what this fundamentally shows is that the order, the pattern in which the whole
creation is made is fundamentally human-shaped.
Right. The pattern is human. The pattern is human, which means the logos is human. Right.
Right. The logos is human. And it is this divine human logos that is made flash in the
person of Jesus Christ.
As the Father say, without change or alteration, which is again another mind bending concept
that we've talked about a number of times, you know, that the incarnation is eternal.
Right.
So the perfect image of God in Christ is also the perfect humanity.
Yeah, he's the man.
The man.
At the same time.
And this means that Christ is both the origin of humanity in being the pattern through
which humanity, the rest of creation and the relationship between humanity and the rest
of creation comes
to being, and he's the tellos, right, the end, the purpose, the goal of humanity, right? Theosis
of the Orthodox Church means becoming by grace what Christ is by nature. Christ in His person
is the perfect union of God and man, right? And so we become by grace, meaning our humanity is
united to God perfectly in Christ.
And we experience that through the participation in the work of God in the world.
And this is what it means that Christ is the Alpha and the Omega, the first and the last,
the beginning and the end.
It's really astonishing just to contemplate that.
Right.
Yeah.
And I know this is mind-bending stuff we just did in the first half.
I'm about to not help.
If you want to read more about this, read St. Maxima's The Confessor.
Yeah.
not easier to understand than what I just said. No, but that is to read of St.
Fotius, the great, you know, one of the greatest scholars in the history of the Orthodox
Church, he described St. Maximus as being like a labyrinth. Like he felt lost. So yeah.
So this is, this is how he stepped, but this is right. This is the key to understanding
way in which the father is the
in which the church, the way in which Christianity, frankly, this is why the person of Christ is
at the center of all seven councils. Seven ecumenical councils. Because this is the key. Christ, the
person of Christ is the key to understanding everything, literally, the creation. And he's
These are ways to come to know God.
So literally everything. And this is St. Paul comes back to this again and again and again
and again, right? In him all things hold together, right? Through whom and for whom and
to whom all things are created, right? Yeah. Talking about Christ. This isn't just rhetorical
flourish. Yeah, he's not some object floating in space. He's the one who fills all in all.
Right, and this isn't a love song.
Maybe you're everything to me. You're the sunrise. You're the sunset. Right. That's not what's good.
Right. This is this is actual community of communicative. This is trying to convey who Christ is. Yeah.
This is big. Like this is bigger than
and and and the role he plays. Not just rhetorical flourish. Right. And so as heavy as this is and
And the reason...
why statements about this like from like the ones from St. Paul, I was just referencing sound
almost rapsotic, almost himnic sometimes is because this is so big and so heavy. Yeah, poetry,
the enormity of it. Yeah, poetry is kind of the only way to talk about this. No? Yeah, yeah,
the sheer enormity of it, right, is something that can, right, um...
And again, again, this is not this thing that Christians come up with in the fourth century.
Right. This is something in the Hebrew Bible that was understood by
Jewish people's centuries before the birth of Jesus.
Right. They understood it. Right. They understood who the divine logos was. They had these ideas.
Right, they hadn't met him yet.
But so what the New Testament is saying, what St. Paul is saying, what the gospels are saying is,
now we've met him.
Yeah.
And he became flesh and dwelt among us.
All right.
Well, with all of that, while you ponder that a little bit, we're going to take our first
and it will be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of
Spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Ancient Faith Radio is brought to you by our listeners with help from
Faith Tree Resources. Have you ever felt distracted or disengaged in
search, but...
weren't quite sure what to do about it.
Divine Liturgy, the greatest invitation,
is the newest video course brought to you
from Faith Tree Resources,
and will help you better understand
and experience the peace God offers to us
in the Divine Liturgy.
This four-part series, taught by some
of the church's most respected leaders,
will equip you with resources and tools
to help you more deeply encounter the one true God.
Whether you're a parent, hungry to teach your children,
a pastor looking to equip your faithful
or someone who wants...
learn how to actively be present in the Divine Liturgy, this course is for you.
Go to...
Ancient Faith Radio is brought to you by our listeners, with help from Faith Tree Resources.
Have you ever felt distracted or disengaged in church, but weren't quite sure what to
do about it?
Divine Liturgy, the greatest invitation, is the newest video course brought to you from Faith
Tree Resources, and will help you better understand and experience the Peace God offers to us
in the Divine Liturgy.
This four-part series, taught by some of the church's most respected leaders, will equip you with resources and tools to help you more deeply encounter the one true God.
Whether you're a parent, hungry to teach your children, a pastor looking to equip your faithful, or someone who wants to learn how to actively leave you present in the divine liturgy, this course is for you.
Go to faithtree.org to get your copy today. That's faithtree.org.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Hey welcome back.
And we'll all over again.
I know.
What happened?
Those faith tree people must have paid like 75% extra for that.
Remember this, we got it
kid engineering the show, he's got small fingers, small hands,
doing his best. Wow, really throw them under the bus, it's
great. He's never going to want to do this again. Like, no,
forget that's people.
Welcome back everybody. Yeah, so feel free to give us a ring
855 AF radio, a 552372346, just like the voice of Steve just
said, although I don't know, should we call him the voice of Steve
anymore.
Like
I think he feels a little bad, like people meet him and like,
are you the voice of Steve?
I mean, I'm sure he'd rather they say,
aren't you the B the B guy, which is what he got before, right?
So, I don't know.
I knew the job was dangerous when he took it.
That's right.
Yeah.
My boss was just saying that to me the other day.
Infraurapanian, for a pound.
That's right.
Because apparently there was some show called Super Chicken,
which was like a subtle show.
Yeah, yeah.
Apparently the line you need...
this job was dangerous when you took it is in that that show.
Buck, super chicken.
Yeah.
That was a reference.
I didn't know until Melinda mentioned it to me, which she was so happy that she knew
a pop culture reference that I did not.
So I was like, well, you know, welcome to my world.
She was happy she knew a pop culture reference that you didn't.
Correct.
Exactly.
Shiguro, not that we're here to talk about, but Shiguro.
up in a Sweden-Borgin, you know, enclave or whatever.
Yeah, okay.
But that's like, you know, they weren't, hey, I have the words world-stall as short person.
I mean, I mean, they weren't watching Hannah Barbarra.
If she knew one, I didn't know.
That would be something to brag about.
But of course, I have heard of Super Chicken.
Right.
And even mimicked his battle cry moments ago.
Indeed.
So.
Yes.
All right.
He looked super chicken. Yeah. I mean,
not his flavor. I don't know. I don't know if he's a
major. Yeah. I remember danger mouse.
Yeah. So oddly enough, we actually do have some calls coming in.
All right. So yeah, are they coming from inside the house?
I don't see anyone in my studio. No, this one I think is coming from Tennessee.
So we've got Will who's calling and he has a question about
Sofia
and logos which yeah yeah so we'll welcome to the Lord of Spears podcast. Thank you Father,
can you hear me? We hear you. Fantastic. So question I suppose the first
stuff just to clarify for myself is when we're talking about Sophia as betrayed and prof herbs and
and wisdom of Syrac and we're talking about the logos.
All right, do those have...
the same reference, those are both Christ.
Yeah, in those kind, I'd have to look at what passage in Syracia talking about.
Oh, yeah, yeah.
Proverbs and yes.
Yes, because sometimes if I'm not mistaken, sometimes doesn't, or maybe some of the
fathers, I'm not sure, refer to wisdom and identify that as being the Holy Spirit.
But in this case, it is the divine logos.
It is Christ, son of God.
Right.
And we have plenty of him to talk about Christ.
is the wisdom and word and power of God.
Yes, from the Paschal Canon, for instance.
All right, so, following up on that, in that passage in Proverbs, when it's referring
to Sophia, it is using Steminin terminology.
They're Steminin, I believe it starts out within a verse one or two, but when the
The logo is using masculine terminology.
My question is, one, is this...
important source, this just like some grammar thing of different languages have different
grammar and so those are just grammatically one as a feminine and one as masculine. But
if it is important then what's what's going on there? Why is when we're thinking about
it as Sophia is it portrayed in the scripture as feminine whereas when I talked about logos
it's referred to in masculine terms.
It's really just chromatical gender like it has like
like why is a table female or feminine in French? It's nothing particularly feminine about tables.
It's just the grammatical gender really. Yeah. Did we lose you there? No, no, I'm still here.
Like really, really are you sure? Yeah. And part of part of the issue here is that
in Anglophone America in particular,
this has become this huge bizarre political thing,
not recently, I mean over the last 70 years.
I mean, the whole pronouns thing is relatively recent,
but this sort of hyper focus on gender
and its relation to sex.
I mean, the bigger question in this proverb's passage
is how come the verb yellowed it means
to give birth to keeps getting used to refer to God, the Father. Yeah.
Fathers don't give birth to children.
Right? Yeah.
Yeah. So that's not the normal use of the language. Right?
You can't absolute times. Right.
And so yeah.
So, this passage is very clearly sort of comfortable.
using these terms that normally be feminine, right?
And you can't avoid that with the way we talk
about the Holy Trinity.
Right? We say begotten of the Father.
Christ has not has a mother on the terms of His divinity.
He has a mother in terms of His humanity.
Right? We have that hymn,
Investors, it says He's without mother on the side
of his father and without father on the side.
of his mother. Right? So yeah, the scriptures are fairly comfortable with that. There's not,
it's not making any kind of political or gender or feminist statement when it uses this kind of
feminine language about God or language it's typically used about women for God. It just does.
That's that sort of
I hang up we have as modern people one way or another.
Um, specific, almost entirely specific to the United States.
Yeah.
It looks like we, uh, we actually lost Will, but hopefully he heard you hear me.
Oh, yeah, we got you back.
Okay.
Yeah.
I was lost, but now I am found.
Um, hopefully you're aligned.
And now you see.
Well, I see better after listening to these podcasts.
So I am one of those people who made the
Peter Thin, Pajot, Lord of Spirits, pipeline.
And I know one thing that the Pajot talk quite a bit about is about masculine feminine that.
Nope.
We lost you again, Will.
What was that click?
I don't know, that's, yeah.
Oh dear.
Are you back now?
Sorry.
Yeah, I will try to make this quick because I don't know what is happening, but they talk
about how the pages talk a lot about reduced masculine feminine down very narrowly to just
talking about sex and particularly focusing on human sex.
But that's a much broader concept and that's more of a relational concept.
And I was wondering if those are talking about...
different perspective of relationships or something like that. Right, right. It's talking about
it's not the relationship between God and his wisdom. We would say between the Father and the Son.
Right. And even though it's a little bit of a weird use of the term and that that would usually
be used to refer to a mother in a son, right, that verb, right. It correctly describes the
the relationship because it
trying to differentiate that relationship from something that's created or made, right?
That's external.
Yeah, right. Whereas giving birth, that's an internal, right?
A function.
All righty. Well, thank you and I'm going to take my lead before I'm picked off again.
like man I've been playing
Alan Wake 2 and that clicker's freaking me out.
I'm in the only room in the church with a light on too.
This is a man.
There's a squirrel calling from somewhere inside the church.
Do recommend the Alan Wake game anyway.
They've made no promotional.
But if they'd like to, I'm here.
Indeed, indeed.
All right.
Well, um,
all right.
Well, why don't we go ahead and roll on and, um,
Yeah so...
It's hard to summarize what we talked about in the last half but hopefully you were listening.
Yeah, I'm just tuning it now. Sorry.
This is going to be a rough order.
True.
It's true.
But we talked a lot about Proverbs 8, 22, 3, 31, which is what we're just discussing
with the well.
Yeah.
And how Christ is the wisdom who is the basis of the order of the world.
I think that's probably the best way to summarize.
So we just said...
so much more. But yes, yes, right. So yeah, we were talking about, I mean, basically, in a nut shell,
I do not know what kind of nut has a shell such as this, but in a nut shell, we're talking about
what order is. We say that God created the universe by putting it in order. What is that order we're
talking about and ultimately that order
that pattern, that logos, that wisdom is Christ.
Right, it's the birth of Christ.
That's my nutshell summary, right?
What we...
Okay.
Yeah.
And so now we're going to turn here in the second half to looking at how that order in creation
functions.
Right?
So this half we're going to be talking about the meaning of life, briefly, which is
you
Everybody knows is 42.
Yes. And as I said to you earlier, the thing that disappoints me about that reference is that the part that's really funny to me is what comes after that in context, which is that right.
They create this planet size computer that they have churning to just determine the meaning of life, the universe and everything over like century. I think it's millennia.
And it finally spits out the answer, the answer is 42.
Right. And the immediate response is that all of the universe's philosophers, theologians,
scholars, and thinkers all begin to now study what is the question, the answer to which
is 42 that explains the meaning of life, the universe, and everything. Right. So like
It solved nothing.
Getting the answer, right?
Because sometimes it's the journey.
not the destination people and the friends we made along the way. So long and takes for all the fish.
So, meaning in life, meaning, meaning. See, it's hard to talk about meaning without using the word
meaning. Like what does meaning mean? You know? But so what does it mean to even
can ask the question about the meaning of life, an individual life, life in general, the
meaning of the world. What does it mean to try to uncover the order and the pattern of
the world? You can just give the right answer based on the first half and say it's Jesus.
But now you have to do what all those philosophers and the allotions and scholars had to do. Now
I have to come up with the right question.
to understand the answer.
Right?
So we're moving on to what's the question, what's the right question?
Right.
So we've talked before, now we're going back to another episode, pick up some more threads
from I think the episode about the news is where we talked about this.
About the order that is out in the world, in the world around us and the nature of things
there is a
a system or a web of relationship, relationships between people and things in the world.
Right?
And it is within that system and web of relationships that any given person or thing finds its identity.
What it is. Right?
This is an important concept.
Right. Because the way most of us have been taught to think about, and there's a heavy
amount of Aristotle in this, right, is that what a thing is, right, the identity of a
person or a thing, right, an object, anything, is based on some kind of internal patterning
of the object.
Right.
So it's something that's internal to the object or internal to the person.
Who a particular person is, their identity is something internal to them.
It's sort of what we've been taught.
And this is the opposite of the case, right?
So if we imagine an island in the middle of the Pacific where no humans have ever been,
Right.
And we imagine that there is a naturally occurring shard of metal laying somewhere on it that is shaped like a hammer.
Okay, shaped like a hammer.
That object is not a hammer.
But, but it's not even an object shaped like a hammer until someone sees it.
Yeah, this is on some level.
This is the if a tree falls in the forest and no one is around to hear it.
Does it make a sound?
phenomenologically, the answer to that, of course, is no, because sound has to be heard
to be a sound.
Right.
Yes.
Yeah.
It will create vibrations of the air, but that's not a sound.
But so that object is just an object, right?
Well, it enters into some system of relationships with something
else. Right? So if a crab has to crawl over it, right, it is still not a hammer. Now it's
an obstacle. Right? Because the crab has to go around it or go climb over it or whatever.
Right? And when the crab is gone, it ceases to be anything really. Right? It is just an object.
And yes, it doesn't cease to exist.
right in the modern sense of existence.
Right continues to have all of the mathematical right you could you could go.
But again, this would require you to go see it.
But hypothetically, if you went and saw it, you could take the measurements,
you could do all those things.
And even when you weren't looking at it, it would maintain those measurements and
everything. Right.
Um, but it wouldn't be anything in particular.
And any given object.
actually be a variety of different things.
Sure. I mean, you know, how many people here haven't used a screwdriver as a hammer at some point?
Yeah, yeah, which please don't do that. Or if I walk out, you know, in my front lawn and I find a hammer,
right, I can say, I'm going to use this for a hammer, right? I can say, I'm going to use this
the crack wall nuts it's gonna be my nut cracker. I can say I'm gonna use this as a weapon to go
knock around my neighbor who's been bothering me, right?
And so whether this is a food utensil,
a household tool for driving nails,
or a weapon, depends entirely on me as a human,
right, as a human observer and an actor
and how I choose to relate to this object.
Right?
I could even fail to recognize that it's a hammer.
I'm going to say, oh, there's some piece of metal trash here in my yard and interact with
it. Is that?
Yeah.
Especially if you've never seen one before, maybe.
You know, so you have no intentions for that shape.
Or if it's rusted and corroded, right?
Yeah.
Or entices or whatever, you know.
Right.
And so it has its identity within this system of relationships.
Abstracted from all those relationships, it isn't anything.
Right.
which I know is hard for people to understand, but consider again the problem of the set of molecules
that you're carrying around right now, those all belong to something else, they were put in
relationship to something else and were something else. So this works on the macro level too, not just
the sort of the molecular or atomic level. Yes, yeah. Yeah. And this is observable
with familiar
objects, right? So if I have an object that used to belong to my father who has now departed
this life, right? Even if it's a random object like a stapler, right? That stapler is something
different to me because bold up within our memories of my father that may have nothing to do
do with stapling things, right?
But...
Because it was his stapler.
There are all these things that when you see that stapler
are simply do not exist for you.
That probably don't exist for anyone but me
and maybe my siblings and my mother.
Like if they even recognized it as my dad's stapler,
which they might not,
in which case it would be gone for them too.
And then when you move to people,
Right.
Uh.
People can look at my wife and see that she's a woman.
Right.
But I look at her and I see my wife.
That is different.
She is someone different to me than she is to other people.
Right.
So this is just a reality in our everyday lives.
And when we try and take a materialist, scientific kind of view of...
the world, we're just denying all of these things. We're trying to fake denial of all these
things. Right. But there's still true to us. Right. I don't care how much of a scientist
you are, you value the lives of your close family members more than people you've never met
and never will. Yeah. You may feel horribly guilty about that, but it's the truth.
Right? These are just truths, right, of how we operate in the world. And we couldn't
operate otherwise. If we try to interact with everyone and everything in the world, based
on it's like mathematically computable measurements and that's it. With no associated memories,
with no intent, with no relational
subjective element, like you couldn't function in the world.
Right, you wouldn't be a human at least to be a Rumba, right?
Like, this may be the first Rumba reference on the podcast.
My, my vacuum clear is named Rosie.
She has doogly eyes.
She vacuums the floor.
But even though I have personified her, she is not a person.
She is operating based on mathematics and is not even really
a sheet. Right. So that's just my sexism, jeevacuum, so I'm so and so any sense of meaning
and purpose for anything or anyone requires an external observer. Yeah, there has to be
a relationship in place. Right. That's to be an external observer. Louisette the thing,
and related
to it in some way. And there is no view from nowhere as we've talked about. The second most
common quotation from Thomas Nagel, that's honest, so. Right. Okay. And for there to be a human order,
we talked about how the order of creation is a human order. Right. That requires a human observer.
Because the first most common quote we don't know what it's like to be a bat.
We know that a bat perceives the things in the world according to its own relational qualities,
but we don't know what that is because we're not a bat, right?
But we know what it is to be human.
And so we observe things, we give things purpose, we utilize them according to the human
mode of understanding and consciousness.
put things into that human order.
But when we're talking about putting things in order,
so we talked about in the first half,
that the way human beings participate in this
is by continuing the work of God participating
in the work of God in the world
to put things in order and fill them with life.
On this level of order, there are two inseparable elements
One of them is a passive recognition of the order that already exists in the world.
We don't come to the world as this sort of clean slate that we get to then connect all
the dots, however we want.
Yeah, you're born into a world that exists.
That is already ordered to some extent, rightly or wrongly.
Oh
already a system of relationships in place between people and things.
And so we come to passively recognize that order.
But the other inseparable element is our actively putting things in order.
Our actively, relationally interacting with and through the things in the world, interacting
with other people.
Right. Which serves to shift the order of things in one direction or another to establish order where it's breaking down to short it up. Right. And these two things always go together.
Right.
So what does this mean in terms of the meaning of life? And there he used the verb, or I use the word mean. Right. What does this mean again? But.
All right.
So on one hand, there are people.
who approach questions of meaning and purpose,
and the meaning of life,
from the perspective purely of that kind of passive discovery.
Yeah, meaning is out there, we have to find it.
I mean, this is the same idea behind when people say things
like words mean things.
That this is what they mean by that.
I'm gonna go find myself.
Alright, yeah, there we go.
that is what I am.
Yeah, like the sense of,
like it's an archaeological activity.
Yes, you know.
The truth is out there.
I will go find it.
Exactly.
But in a way where we're totally passive, right?
There is some meaning of life.
I'm going to learn what it is passively.
God or someone wise or something is going to tell me,
is going to inform me.
Some experience I have is going to cause me
to see what
it all means, right? And so that is wrong, right? Because that is taking purely that passive
approach. The other pull is to take only the active approach, right? Where meaning formation
and purpose formation is the triumph of the will. This is Nietzsche frankly, right? I am going to go
out and I am going to order the world after my own will.
World, at least order my world.
Right.
I will force it to become what I desire it to be.
It is just all moldable, all malleable.
I can actively shape it into whatever I want.
Right.
And people have varying degrees of success with that.
Some people like Napoleon have pretty good runs and then the run ends.
Right.
But you keep, you keep getting confronted by the non-mailiable parts, right?
So that is also an error, right?
That is also an error.
So the reality is in between the active and the passive taking place at the same time,
right?
where as we actively live and make choices and give order to our
lives and to the world around us, we also discover the order that is already there and discover
how we fit. These two things happen at once. So this doesn't mean, right, this doesn't mean.
We can also take those two poles and talk about variety and lack thereof.
So views which say the order, the meaning, whatever is out there is completely out there.
And we just have to find it. That tends to mean that the order and the meaning that are out there
are very general. Right? People who think of that when talking about the meaning of life,
not the meaning of my life. Yeah, yeah, yeah. Right. So the idea is that this meaning,
this order is kind of general.
right? It's for everybody. Right? There's just this one order. Right? Yeah, it's
every rose has its thorn. Yes. The night has its dawn. Yeah. Every cowboy. See the sad song.
So then the other side, right, the sort of I'm going to shape the world to my will is very
individualistic. Right, I'm going to assert my meaning in the world but...
That's my meaning, not yours.
Right?
It's over against yours if you even have one.
If you even have the kind of will that I have.
Right?
And so then there's this sort of infinite variety of orders
to which the world could be subjected by your will.
Right?
Which is kind of trying to make you
an unfettered creator god, which good luck with that.
Right? And so again, neither of these poles is accurate. Right? So what we have, when
you have both the active and the passive working together, is you don't have a variety of orders,
but you have a variety of instances of a pattern, of the same pattern. And I think a good
visual example of this, drawing it back to what we were talking about in the first half.
is in orthodox iconography of the saints.
Yeah, yeah.
Because they look different,
but they kind of all look the same as well.
Right. Right. There's this level where they all look the same,
and that's deliberate. That's not bad art.
Right. That's not stylistic. Right.
They look the same because these are all humans
who have been formed into the image.
of Christ. They've been formed into the same image, logos, Christ. Right? And so they all
kind of look the same. But at the same time, they're all different people who have been so
formed. And so they all look a little different. Right? And so the saints sow as myriad ways
of being Christlike in different places times situations.
For man.
for women, for children, for elderly people, right,
for people in between, right, all the way across the gamut,
right.
And the, the, the fulfill our purpose, right?
If our purpose is to humanize the world,
if our purpose is to turn the world into a garden,
if our purpose is to put everything else in order,
first, humanization of the world requires the humanization of humanization,
the humanization of human-
humans. Yeah, and I think that, you know, we're going to get into application a lot in
the third half, but just as a piece of application here, everybody wants to change the world, as
it says, but no one thinks of changing himself. You know, there's an order in which that says
to happen. We can't effectively make the world in the way that God desires us to, if
We're not.
already on the path to holiness ourselves. It just doesn't, doesn't work. So one can have a lot of opinions
and do a lot of things, but unless one is actually engaged in this humanization for oneself, it's going
to end up being distorted because you're going to shape it according to how you are. Yeah. Although I
heard the saying is everybody wants to change the world, but nobody wants to change the toilet paper
Also true. Yeah. If they do, they hang it up backwards. And then you're like, what?
Yes. Right. So this means for there to be any kind of broader meaning to the universe,
So the cause of right there first has to be a meaning to your human life, right?
And that isn't something...
that's just discovered that's something that's discovered and constructed at the same time.
But this isn't an individual human life, for the reasons we've just described,
that abstracted from relationships, no one and nothing is anything.
Right.
So if you are a
completely alienated and isolated and alone as our culture is desperately trying to do to you.
Right. You're going to have all kinds of issues about your identity.
Because you're not in active relationships with other humans,
which is what that identity is based on. Right. And so, for meaning to happen,
it has to happen in terms of not just human life, but communal human life.
You're a man.
to be together. I mean, you come into this world with a communal relationship, namely your mother.
I think it is inescapable. Right. And that communal life is active, it's dynamic, it's participatory.
Right. And on our own or nothing, this is why
Why the church was established.
talking about the assembly of Israel and the Torah that we're going to talk about the third half,
or we're talking about the churches we know it today. Yeah, and even, I mean, even the ancient
concept of what a person is, I could reflect it in both Greek and Latin. The word in Greek for
person generally is prosopon and then Latin its persona and both of these refer to the face.
So if you think about this for a second, your face is not really available to you.
It's only available to the people around you who see your face.
And I mean, now we have mirrors.
And so we have this idea of seeing our own faces.
But mirrors that exist in the ancient world weren't super common and they weren't that
great.
So most people never really saw what they truly looked like.
Only other people.
And so even the ancient idea of a person.
is about relationship with other people. Right. Right. And this can't be emphasized
enough, right, that that just like in the Old Testament, in the New Testament, a community
is formed. Christ doesn't ascend to heaven and leave a book for people to go and read
you didn't find all the answers.
Right.
About life and its meaning and whatever else.
He creates a community, right?
A community in which scriptures are read, in which there's a way of life that is practiced,
right?
In which there are rituals that bring the community together and bind them together and
bind them together to God.
That's what Christ leaves.
That's what He sends His apostles to do, right?
That's how this meaning is.
formed. And so, again and again, we have to point out because our culture is so aimed at alienating
and isolating everyone and leaving them alone, right, because then you're easily manipulable.
You could be told who you are. You could be taught to express who you're supposed to be now by
what you consume, etc. We've talked about this before.
Right? In the face of that, the answer to that, this sounds overly simple, but it's
go to church. Yeah. Yeah, I think it's really that simple.
One of the big problems of our, I think one of the reasons why we're so fragile, and by
this, I'm not just saying, you know, you guys are much of snowflakes. Although kind of,
Now, is because we have so
If you or so shallow relationships, right, anti-fragility is about a dynamism of a complex
web of relationships, right?
Like if there's only one person who's opinion you care about, if that opinion shifts in a
way that's negative, it's going to be devastating for you.
But if you are within a web of relationships of people who love you and value and interact
with you and admire you and respect you and treat you as a human.
And then one of them kind of goes off the deep end.
You can handle that much better because of that whole web of relationships that you're
in.
You have resilience because of that.
And I think that one of the things that the sort of late capitalism age that we're in
has done, as you said, Father, you know, is isolating everybody.
So it's increasing fragility because
is we have fewer relationships and our relationships are not as deep.
So it really is a problem.
And I think it's creating these crises of meaning and understanding meaning, which of course
is what this whole episode is about.
Yeah.
And there are internet communities out there, for example, that are really trying to keep
this plate spinning.
and are really trying to keep.
isolated and alienated people out there from completely losing their minds, right?
Sure. And going off the deep end and going into self-harm, and it's good that they're doing that.
But those aren't a substitute for real community. Those are trying to do triage. Those are
those communities are trying to do, you know, intensive care for people who really need in person
then community and relationships.
It's like, it's like, you know, if someone's...
If someone's suicidal and they happen to you know, thank God call a suicide hotline
And there's a voice on the other end talking to them that you know God willing helps them not to do that thing
That's good
But it's nothing like
If there's someone there with them
You know, right we only reason why that works is somewhere they don't need to call a stranger
Yeah, right when they reach that point exist is because of the ice right?
Yeah, yeah, so it better to have someone.
and you can. Yes, right. You can. The church is maybe the last place. The Union halls are gone.
All those other stuff is gone. That used to provide community, the neighborhood pub, right.
All that's been stripped away, right? But the church can still be that.
So what does this all mean? This means that as I said at the beginning.
beginning of this half, right, trying to formulate the question, right, to which Christ in the
meaning he embodies is the answer, right, is that the way we formulate the question
is by actively living. By actively giving meaning to our life and discovering the meaning
that is already discovering the order that's already in the world.
discovering who other people are and how they relate to us,
discovering the things in the world and how they relate to us,
and being discovered by them.
And then through that, making a life,
crafting a life,
I'll say something nice about Jean Paul Sartre.
Right?
Jean Paul Sartre once said that by making choices,
you can make your life a-
Melody, which is a little fru-fru, but
But what he's saying there is
That you could live your life in a way that's intentional
Yeah, that gives it meaning that gives it beauty that gives it purpose
Right, but that inquires not just a passive
Approach but an active
an active approach.
Approach in which...
we struggle to embody the order that is in the world, that we struggle to embody who Christ is.
This is what justification being put in order ourselves. This is what justification is about.
This is what repentance is about. Getting ourselves right first. So meaning is discern and
created at the same time. And ultimately the end of the day.
as we pursue this path, the meaning we find is embodied in us because we become a human person.
Right. And in becoming a human person, because Christ is the human person. Right. We also become
Like Christ, we also are united to God in Christ, right?
We also find salvation.
Yeah.
All right, well, I know these first two halves have been pretty heavy stuff, but it's going to,
it's going to become much more applicable in the third half. So you've come this far.
We're glad you're here with us. We're going to go ahead and take our second and final break,
and we'll be back with the third half of the Lord of Spirits.
3-7-2-3-4-6. That's 855-AF Radio.
What are we to make of the unseen world and spiritual warfare?
The Lord of Spirits, book version, is now available at store.hnfaith.com, written by Father
Andrew Stephen Damick.
So the modern mind, dragons and demons are j-
just the inner demons of psychology.
And angels are often reducible to the better angels
of our nature, that is to our better human impulses
and virtues.
Talk of spirits is really about psychology.
But to the ancient mind of millennia ago,
even up to the pre-modern mind of just centuries ago,
these are real beings with personal presence
who inhabit our world and affect us.
Other Andrews.
provides a distillation and explanation of the material in the popular podcast The Lord
of Spirit, which he co-hosts with Father Stephen DeYoung.
Get this brand new book today at store.AncientFaith.com.
That's store.AncientFaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-237-
three, four, six.
That's eight, five, five, a, f, radio.
I don't even know that that commercially existed.
You drug that poor man out of retirement
just to introduce you.
No, I didn't.
Hasn't he suffered enough?
Hasn't his reputation?
Been drug enough without you associating it with yourself.
Ha, ha, ha.
Yeah, I mean, yeah, I wouldn't have done the plug earlier
if I had no nose, we're gonna...
here and Ed from John Maddox himself.
Yeah, that, I mean, that does, you know,
it's a little redundant, I don't know, but yes.
With the clip from the audiobook everybody, by the way.
Oh, it's not a quiz.
Yeah, yeah, right now you can only get the paperback,
but the ebook and the audiobook should be available
within weeks.
We're not sure exactly when,
but God willing, they'll be out there,
but yeah, you can get the paperback right now.
So,
So that's the end.
Does the audio book come with a gag reel?
Only from the forward.
Okay.
I see I've wanted to do a gag reel.
I've suggested it.
I'm going to peel back the curtain.
Oh, I'm going to peel back the curtain.
To this, a worker protest.
Folks who have purchased my audio books,
write to father Andrew and ancient faith.
Oh, man.
and let him know.
that you believe in my freedom to do bits and make jokes during my audiobook
readings. They have been stifling my creativity and making me just read the
text of the book and not allowing me to do clevericides. So if you want my
clevericides, right, to Father Andrew, to ban them, you can make an expanded
revised bonus edition of the
book. I got more books coming. They could be at least 27% more entertaining. If I can
we have an army of editors, my friend, to make sure that doesn't happen. That's my point.
That's right. Exactly. People reach out, express your will. Yeah. So all the hate mail comes
to me anyway so yeah well this will just this is the suggestion category
hashtag free father Steven. Yeah. Like free as an audible free speech or free as in free
beer because speech. Okay. Okay. Yeah. Yeah. All right. Well, if you have any of the other
I am Dutch. Um, there you go. Yeah. Yeah. So welcome to third half. Um, now we're going
actually now you're really like wait I thought this was supposed to be supposed to be supposed to
be about biblical interpretation or something. When do we get to the topic before the end?
Yeah, rarely. One out of the five.
We had to start before the foundation of the world to get here to how to read the Bible.
Just how these things work. It's true. It's true. Yeah. So, so now we need to talk about how
This
human mediation of meaning, meaning into the world, right?
Into God's created world.
How that works functionally within the community we were talking about at the end of the last
half, right?
And so we're going to start with Moses.
Right.
So we now at least moved to Exodus from Genesis.
over the course of an hour and a half.
And so Moses is the first leader of the ecclesia
as the Greek of the Old Testament has it, right?
The assembly of Israel, right?
He's the first leader.
And so Moses is the image we get in the Torah
right from the beginning of how human leadership
is going to function within the community of God's people.
And one of the things you notice when you read closely
through the Torah is that the words that God says to Moses and the words that
Moses then says to the people are not identical. Yeah, you can compare them. It's
not simply Moses. They're right there. You're literally one after the other. Yeah,
right, right. God comes and says something to Moses. Very often prefaced with, say
to the sons of Israel.
XYZ. Yeah. Right. Usually relatively
turs. Right. And then Moses goes to the
aforementioned sons of Israel and says
X X one X two Y Z one Z two Z three. Right. Right.
Which on its face might seem like wait
Moses you're not obeying what God said to
do. Right. You're adding to what God said.
you
That's what's that.
Yeah, I had her take away, right?
But the scriptures never treat him that way.
No, no, quite the opposite.
He's doing what he's supposed to be doing.
Right. When he does this, right?
He's creatively engaging with what God said
because this is what he's doing.
He's not changing.
He's not changing it.
He's explaining it by detail.
Fleshing out.
Yeah, right. Applying.
Right. So a good example of this.
is when God commands to Moses and then tells Moses to speak to the Israelites,
concerning the dedication of the firstborn.
Meaning God says, every firstborn male that opens the womb is mine.
This is after the death of the firstborn in Egypt.
He says, therefore, firstborn of any animal you will take and you will sacrifice to me.
Firstborn human son you will go and make this offering instead because he doesn't want human sacrifice, right?
That's what God says to Moses
Then when Moses gives this commandment to the Israelites he flushes it out with all of this detail
one of which detail is
Don't sacrifice donkeys
Did God certainly not say
That was shelt not sacrifice yon donkey
Yeah.
Uh, so this has, right, and this gives you a window into modernist biblical studies,
in that biblical studies people read that.
And here's where they instantly go, right, because this is the hermitidic they've been taught.
Uh-huh.
There must have been some kind of pagan donkey sacrifices going on in ancient Israel.
And a later author is putting into
the mouth of Moses that these donkey sacrifices must stop.
Right.
If you don't believe me, go to a search of journal articles, you'll find them on
donkey pagan donkey sacrifices.
Um, so I'm trying to connect it to Lee Lee, the donkey rider.
Right.
Yeah.
You get all that.
Oh, yeah.
Right.
Yeah.
Two and so forth.
Right.
Hey, everybody.
But again, as usual, if you just read what it says, right?
Let's at least try to take it to face value first.
Right, let's-
see how that goes, then we can do other things. It seems pretty clear that Moses, as he's
explaining this to the people, sees, well, wait a second, there are animals that we don't
sacrifice because they're unclean. Right? So we're going to need to weigh in with an
opinion here. Right? God said every firstborn animal, you sacrifice to him.
Unclean animals were not supposed to sacrifice to him. So what do we do about first born male
unclean animals, right? And so Moses gives a ruling. He says, no, your first born male donkey,
you don't go sacrifice that. You offer this other sacrifice instead when your first born
real donkey comes. Right. This is...
very simple. Right? This is we don't need to do any weird research, right? We don't need
to hypothesize different dates of authorship. Just Moses has to make a ruling, a very practical
ruling. Right? This is a question that would come up. Hey, my donkey just gave birth. Right?
Like, do I sacrifice it? Yeah, right. And Moses as the prophet is the leader appointed by
God is the one who has to make these calls.
And God doesn't expect him to be like, oh, you know, God didn't explicitly mention that.
Let me go. Let me pray on it. Let me go toss the Euroman thumam, right?
And get a ruling on the donkey sacrifices, right? The authority that God has invested him with
is precisely the authority to make these calls.
the authority to apply what God has said to the practical life of the people. So that's a
micro scale example. If you want a macro scale example, and again, this has ridiculously confused
and spawned so many journal articles and dissertations. It's amazing, right?
it in terms of biblical scholarship.
The differences between...
Exodus and Leviticus on one hand and Deuteronomy on the other.
And you could take any particular feast, any particular sacrifice or observance, right?
These must be by different authors. These must have been written centuries apart. These
... Okay. Let's try again. Let's take it at face value. Let's see how that works out before we do
anything else. So what's actually presented in the Torah is happening.
Right. What's presented in the Torah is happening is that Moses speaks to God face to face.
God gives him the Torah. God gives him commandments. And Moses comes in Exodus, at Mount Sinai.
Leviticus also takes place while they're at Mount Sinai, by the way. At Mount Sinai. And
Moses then takes and applies, like we were just talking about, right, with the first born.
And a
applies that to the life that those people are going to live.
Because these people are living,
wandering as nomads in the Sinai Desert
in a camp with the Tabernacle at the center.
So if you're living in a camp in the desert
with the Tabernacle in the center, right?
Then the way you observe Passover,
the way you observe any of the other feasts on the calendar
then involve sacrifices.
That's going to take one shape because you always have access to the tabernacle.
It's right there.
Right.
And these are people who are going to end up living their whole the whole rest of their lives,
living in this camp, living in the desert, moving nomatically.
Right.
Again, taking it face value, what Deuteronomy says is happening is that Moses is
You
Giving the law, giving the Torah again.
That's a Tudoran meme means second law, devleros nomos.
He is speaking to the next generation.
All those people he was talking to at Exodus,
the Vedic is dead except for Joshua and Caleb and himself.
This next generation is about to go into the land
and settle there.
and they're going to settle
all across it. Right. We're going to settle all across Canaan. Some of them are going to settle in the
transjordan. He already knows at the time he's saying this within the text. Right. And so when he
gives instructions, say for observing the Passover, if you're living in the transjordan,
if you're living in Dan, if you're living, right. The tabernacles only going to be in one place.
Is that good?
be near you. So your relationship to the sacrifices the tabernacles about to change, the way
you celebrate the feces is going to have to change. You're going to go to supporting
your family by farming instead of scooping up mana off the ground every morning. There's
to be a whole change in their way of life. And so the same commandments of God, the same
patterns revealed to Moses by God, the same logos.
sat and talked to face to face is going to be applied to a generation of people settled
living in a gray in life in the land in ways that are different in various ways from how
that same logo supplied to them when they were living nomatically in the desert in a camp
with the tabernacle at the center.
radically different. Not black is white white is black. Not this was a sin before.
And now it's wonderful.
It's gonna be consistent.
It's gonna be consistent and not contradictory,
but it's not gonna be identical.
Two different instances of the pattern.
Two different instances of the same pattern
applied to a different generation of people
living a different way of life,
but the same pattern being applied to it,
taking a subtly different shape.
Right? And Moses' job in Deuteronomy.
because he's still alive, right?
I'll tell the very end of Deuteronomy,
is to continue to do that, to take it and apply it.
And in chapter 31 of Deuteronomy,
he gives that, passes that authority on to Joshua.
Right?
Passes that authority on to Joshua, Joshua.
But even within that, this is something with us,
I'd, but we may do an episode on this at some point.
This is the T's.
for the apostolic succession episode that might happen in the future. Even in the context
of Joshua becoming Moses successor, there's the reiteration that there is no profit like
Moses. Yeah. And that there is a difference there as well, like a possible. Right, which
is what we'll get to that. Yes, successors to the other. Aren't just new apostles there.
Right. Sixth of all, but that's a future episode.
Yes. Yes.
That's a, that's a.
bingo card box we haven't checked in a while.
Referencing a future episode.
But there it is.
People were starting to believe
that the podcast really was almost over
because we stopped doing that.
So, that's against keeping some tuning in though, right?
You never know what it'll go away.
Don't know what you got to let's go.
Pay for paradise, put it in a parking lot.
So as we were just speaking about bishops, right?
this role that
we see Moses play, right? This is the role of leadership. This is the role of the bishop in the church.
Right? From Sainting, Nations on. Right? The bishop is there to bind and to lose to rightly divide.
Right? All of these terms that we've extracted from the King James version of the Scriptures.
Right?
To apply the scriptures.
the canons, the teachings of the church, right?
To apply those to the communal life of the church.
Right.
And so,
when you look at the historical life of the church,
we see this vast variety of instances of the same pattern.
Yeah.
You could take the church in Russia in the...
13th century, the church in the Roman Empire in the 7th century, even the church in the
United States today.
The church in Japan in the 18th century, pick your century and your local Orthodox church.
That is an instance of the same pattern.
And notably, they're not identical to...
to each other. They're consistent with each other, right? But they're not identical to each
other. I mean, the more you read church history, the more you see this. Right. Right. And
so, despite this, and part of what we're going to be decrying for the rest of this half,
right, is there is a tendency for people to treat the past applications of bishops, right?
Right.
the ways in which the leadership of the church has applied this pattern to its life, in some particular
place at some particular time and treat that as precedent, as establishing a precedent. What do I
mean by that? By essentially elevating that particular contextualization to the level of the
the logo.
itself. Yeah. Saying that is not part of the contextualization. That is part of the pattern.
Yeah. And it's, you know, as you look at church history, you see this that there are some things
that are constant. For instance, we always have bishops, but there are some things that are not
constant. Like we no longer have the minor clerical role of doorkeeper or exorcist. You know.
So there's there's things that keep going. There's things that don't and there's new things. That's the thing that scares a lot of people is sometimes there's new things that that that are introduced, you know, but they have to be consistent with the pattern in order to be actually orthodox.
Right. You know, you can just there are technologies, right? Yeah. Yeah. At some point we're going to have to come up with an orthodox ethic of engagement on social media.
Yeah, it doesn't just exist.
right, right? But it's not going to get just pulled out of the air either. Right. And we also can't just simply say,
well, you know, anything new is bad. We must not do that because number one is social media because that's right.
But number one, that's just not true. There have been new things in the life of the church. But number two, like, no one is consistent about that.
You know?
Everybody has, when I was younger,
I formulated the idea in my head of what I call the
Luddite line, which is the level of technology I will not,
this past this point, I start to refer to pieces of technology
as this thing.
Right?
This is the point at which I become a Luddite.
I don't do that.
But I mean, people do this in church life too.
Like, well, I'm okay with using codices,
but there better not be some kind of digital thing
being used at that chance stand.
But I mean, codices were of friends.
newfangled technology at some point. I'm sure all the old scroll singers are like,
where do I go? I don't know about that. Shouldn't be turning pages. That's wrong.
You know. Right. But also you can imagine, right, because we have the equivalent now.
Right. Somebody hearing Deuteronomy who had talked to their parents before they died in the desert.
Right. Saying, well, wait, that's not what you said before.
You said we were supposed to celebrate Passover this way. I'm going to keep doing it the
whole way because that's the way God said. Yeah. That's a good way to get the ground
to swallow you up in the Torah. Yes. Right. That's not good. But that's what that's what
people do now. Right? By trying to take, well, this is the shape it took in 19...
century Russia or in my reconstructed imagination from having read a bunch of books or whatever,
therefore this is it.
Yeah, there's always the sense that the church, as I'm experiencing it now in my local
parish, does not measure up to this idea that I have of some other time and place.
Right.
And so to get it this, to get it this, we're going to come in this sort of a little different
direction because we can go now to the level.
of texts. Right? So one question that I still get occasionally, right? Despite the way I
react. And I'm sure Father Andrew gets it once in a while too, is, right? I'm talking about
scripture all the time. Is somebody who'll hear something that's usually they haven't heard before
or that strikes them as odd or that they disagree with? And you get what church Father said it means
X.
Right, whatever you just said. Yeah, right. This is an incoherent question.
Hmm. Now by that, I don't mean this is a dumb question. Yeah, it's understandable. There are no
stupid questions. There are many inquisitive idiots, but there are no stupid questions.
It's not the questions fault. You aren't inquisitive idiot. We'd like to hear from you.
We already have.
Right.
When I made you to here.
question, I mean, the question itself does not make sense. Right. It does not make sense.
Yeah. Because there are presuppositions that undergird the question.
There are things that would have to be true for the question to make sense that aren't true.
Right. Yeah. And one of them is like, it's funny. Like, just think this through for a second, folks.
if if if
Orthodox life equals doing things that
are
Locatable in some text of the church fathers
Then that means because the text of the church fathers did not simply drop out of heaven
Along with the creation of Adam
Then that means that there was some point in the life of the church where
Certain things were not written down with certain church fathers had never been born and yet they it's
They had points, some points said or wrote a new thing.
You know?
And so then you have to decide like, oh well, okay.
So up to this point, it's all like, this is what Orthodoxy is.
And then after that, it's all kind of optional or suspect or whatever.
Like, that's just one level in which this is in coherent, is it doesn't actually, you
could not apply this standard throughout most of church history.
Setting aside the problem that throughout most of church history, most people did not have
even access to the church.
fathers to most of what the even if you were living like let's say you're living relatively
later in the period like if you were St. Gregory Pullamas you still didn't have access to all
the writings of the Church of others he didn't yeah he had the ones he had access to yeah and he
had access to an awful lot compared to 99.9% of Christians exactly exactly we're illiterate
on top of everything. Yeah, but yeah, and I really want to focus on the it means.
X part. Yes, right? It means X, right? It the verse, whatever you want to
plug it for it, the text means X. So this assumes that the church fathers, or any
church leader with teaching authority, when they are interpreting texts,
scripture, and whatever else, are appealing to an external free-floating
objective meaning.
But there is for each text of scripture a meaning that meaning is objective.
It is it is not related to any kind of context.
It is objective.
That's it's free floating out there.
And usually I'm guessing people would say something like through the illumination of the
Holy Spirit, the Church Fathers sees it and grasps it.
and tells it to us.
Right?
But that's not what any of the church fathers thought they were doing.
Or we're doing from their own perspective.
That's not how they thought meaning works.
And it's in coherent in terms of how meaning works.
Right?
The idea that St. Paul, when he wrote his letter to the church in Rome, right?
that essentially what it amounted to was a bunch of lines of code,
that when read properly with the correct kind of spiritual illumination
would reveal to you some truths not contained within the text itself.
Right? That doesn't make sense. That's not coherent. Right? That's not coherent.
What the church fathers did was they took texts.
scripture, other texts, the writings of other church fathers,
previous church fathers, hymnographic texts, whatever else, right?
And they applied those texts to the lives of actual communities,
the communities over which they were leaders.
Yeah. Right. So they took the text
and they applied it, right? And so again, their particular application of that text,
Right.
A particular application of that text is an instance of a pattern.
It is not the pattern itself.
So in St. John Chrysostom, preaches, right, you may be reading a
Flora legion or a quote mine of St. John Chrysostom quotes.
You might be reading it in a book on a topic.
Okay.
But when St. John Chrysostom says most most of St. John Chrysostom's writings,
are bits, pieces, chunks, however much, maybe the whole homily.
Surmans, he stood and he gave and delivered to an actual group of people at the end of
the fourth or beginning of the fifth century in a church, in a place who were dealing with
issues at the time.
Some of them are very topical.
Yeah.
Right.
The homily is on the statues, dealing with current events.
All those things about horse racing and so forth.
Yes. Right.
And he is applying the scripture that he just read that he's preaching on to their
lives. Right.
So to take St. John, Chris,
Ostams, any of his contextualizations into the life of those people to take that and
treated as if it were the scripture himself, itself.
Would probably...
I don't think, St. John Chrysostom was probably too holy to smack you upside the head, right?
But you might get the verbal equivalent from him.
Right. To act like what he said in his homily was the same thing as scripture.
Yeah. Right. He, he, in no way, and they're not getting that from nowhere, right?
That's what he observes the apostles do.
doing in the New Testament.
Yeah.
Paul writes letters to actual people in an actual church
and in actual city, dealing with actual issues.
Yeah, they're not, I mean, just read the epistles.
It's obvious that they're two people.
And from a person, there's a particularity to it.
And I think that's one of the problems is that,
for whatever reason, we often are not comfortable
with that particularity.
We want them to be basically like these philosophers.
who are simply stating principles, abstract, theological principles.
Yeah, exactly.
That are eternally true.
I think to do with human life.
Right.
Yeah, but that's not so the eternal truth has everything to do with human life because it's
Christ.
See our first half.
Yeah.
There's always.
Get separate the two.
There's always what in our dogmatic class.
as we're called the, called the sotyriological motive, which everything that the church fathers
write or the apostles or the prophets is for the salvation of the people who receive it.
It's not just to set up, you know, okay, I've got this theological system in my head, and I want
to put it on paper, it's for people to receive it so that it can be salvific for them.
in their particular lives. Yeah, right. In their working out of the meaning of their life, right,
that we talked about in in the last half. Yeah. And the reason the apostles are doing that in the
New Testament because that's what they saw Moses doing. Right. Right. Right. Right. That's right. That's
That's how leadership works and the people of God, right?
And so if you have...
any of the church fathers. You very quickly realize that another way in which that whole idea of
it means X fails, right, is that the fathers are always talking about there being multiple layers
or levels of meaning to texts. Yeah. All the time, right? Yeah, all the time. Even if it's just at the
sort of basic literal and then spiritual.
level, but then you get way more advanced than that too.
Right.
Yeah.
And sometimes, like just to give one example, you know, this upcoming Sunday in a number
of churches, I'm not, I don't know if it's all of us.
The gospel reading is the good Samaritan.
So I mean, there's a bunch of different ways that the church fathers read this passage,
but like two of them are that the, the man who gets beaten up and is by the side of the
road is the soul.
right, and that the good Samaritan is Christ and that, you know, the innkeeper is the church.
And it gets read that way. For instance, you can find that in St. Theophlact of Oakrid,
who I think is basically just taking that from Christos, and I'll find recall correctly.
But then also, you get
that, uh, exhortation that you should be as the good Samaritan or that you should be
as the inkeeper. That's not completely like it's not identical with saying that the good
Samaritan is Christ, right? You know, it's in a logical sense it's contradictory to say that
the good Samaritan is Christ and should be you. But these are different ways of reading this
to apply it for different purposes. So like talking about yourself as the the the soul that's
beaten up on the side of the road is an important part of application.
And it's about Christ's salvation of you.
But then also, you should be like the Good Samaritan
or you should be like the Inkeeper,
is another side of it, which is okay,
you have a duty to behave this way to your fellow man.
You know, so they're not completely compatible
with each other, there was those readings,
but they're compatible with the overall pattern
of what it means to be saved
and what Christians should be doing.
As one example.
Yeah, yeah.
And so part of the problem
them here with understanding the layers of meaning thing is bluntly bad education.
Yeah. Right. People who have learned, you know, this is, this is why, this will be another one
of those I don't care moments. This is why I'm diffed degrees or such a bad idea.
And you got one. And yeah, in two thirds, two thirds of an almost two.
Yes. This is why I'm diffed degrees or a bad idea.
Yeah.
Because what?
one of the worst things that could be done to someone is to teach them a little about
a topic. Yeah. And an Ebtive degree is one in which you are taught a little about a
whole bunch of topics. Yeah. And I'm fortunate. Little. Yeah. I was going to say unfortunately
sometimes people, I mean, I'm guilty of this. clergy think that their favorite subject
and seminary, they are an expert on that because they've studied it in seminary. You
Yeah.
Falling.
It's supposed to be a broad sampling of stuff.
That's what it is.
It's a survey.
Yes.
And the little bit that you get taught
about protistic biblical interpretation is what?
Is there's antioxidant, there's Alexandria.
Yeah.
Which yeah, and Alexandria, they interpret things allegorically
and antioxidant interpret things literally, right?
Yeah, which is no more simplification as it is.
It's just it's bunk home.
Yeah.
It's nonsense.
It is false.
is literally not true, right?
Again, first of all, literal and allegorical
are not opposed to each other.
That's not a choice you have to make.
That's not a choice anyone made.
Okay, actually read some of origins,
got origin, Mr. allegory, read some of his commentaries.
He talks about the literal beating all the time.
He's also talks about
about other additional levels of meaning.
Reed St. John Chris Austin, he never uses an allegory.
Is that what you're gonna tell me?
Cause he's from Antioch.
Yeah, right.
It's nonsense.
Yeah.
And it gives this impression to people
having learned that nonsense
that allegory and literal are opposed to each other.
And they're not.
No, right?
Malibory is a mode of app
It is a way of taking a text that does not seem to have any immediate
direct application to the life of your community and applying it to your community.
Okay. Do not eat. The owl, the knight hawk, or the sparrow has no direct application to my
parish community here in Lafayette, Louisiana. Because they are not bound by kosher food laws
and they're agents.
They'll eat an owl at eye talker as sparrow if they darn well want to.
Yeah.
Fry it up.
It'll taste good with enough hot sauce.
Right.
Tabasco.
All good.
Right.
But that doesn't mean that Texas now like irrelevant.
I can go through and talk about in a Bible study on Leviticus.
Right.
The food laws.
Why they were what they were.
Right?
how they're structured, and I can bring things out of those structures,
maybe use it a little bit of allegory that are applicable and are helpful to the life of my community now.
Right?
So allegory is literal plus.
Hmm.
Right.
And we even have to define literal because what passes for literal now
in our modern world in certain circles.
Literal.
means, what would the average bonehead reading this in English
think? So that's number one. What is the plain meaning of the
text if you just read it to someone in English? Right. And it's
so funny. Sometimes people, if it's not super obvious to
something people like we'll say things like, well, you're
confusing people. Because because this could be read in some
wacky way arcane well, yes, yeah, like, well, welcome to all of
Yes, any text it could be written
in an infinite number of ways.
Right.
That's what literal means.
Or literal means you take some scientific materialist interpretation of it.
That's literal.
Right.
Neither of those is literal.
You can go and read St. Augustine's literal interpretation of Genesis.
That'll tell you what literal is.
Literal is the original context.
Yeah.
That's the literal level of meaning.
This is what it meant in its original context.
When Moses said this to them at the foot of Mount Sinai,
or on the plains of Moab, right?
When Christ said this to the people of Galilee,
standing on a hill, right?
That's the literal meaning, right?
And if you deny that by the way,
if you've denied that original context,
not going to get there very far.
In terms of understanding and applying the text, we just toss that out for some bizarre
reason, right?
Okay, that's the literal meaning.
And so then the further layers of meaning, the other levels of meaning, the spiritual
meanings, the allegorical meanings, right?
These are new and renewed contexts into which the text is being applied.
Alright.
And of course, we now have the issue that we're living more than a millennium after the
vast majority of the church fathers, meaning they themselves have to be interpreted and
applied.
I have to look at what St. John Chrysostom was saying about the statues and what was going
on with the statues, right, in the Roman Empire, the end of the fourth century.
I have to understand that in its original context and then I have to apply that in today's
content.
Yeah, how do I don't have an emperor with statues of himself? I was gonna say how do I play that to municipal art? Yeah
Right, there's a move there that has to happen right that's happened and
The bishops of the church are the one charged with making that move and they delegate
partially some of that teaching authority to the pressmeners who they send out to represent them in the parishes
Right, it's how church government works
So an example of this.
Then I like to give because it's part of my dissertation, right?
Part of my dissertation I look what it everyone ever say about one John 2 verse 2, right?
And so
What you find in most of the church fathers who comment on first John 2 verse 2 is they say something on the order of
Here's St. John refutes the donatists
Right, like with...
fourth century donatists. Yeah, I was gonna say remember everybody the donatists are from hundreds of
years after this New Testament. And if you read what the church father say, they're not just saying like,
oh here say John refutes the error that people like the donatists made. They're saying the
fourth century donatists in Africa, like they're very specific that say John is refuting them.
Yeah, these dotted to churches in Africa.
And by that, they don't mean
See?
John is prophetically predicting that Donatism will exist and giving a response to it.
Right. And writing this verse for that. And therefore, so like, would bead rights that,
the venerable bead rights that in the sixth century, right? He's not saying, oh yeah,
that was about those African Donatists in the fourth century. So now just don't worry about that
verse. Just skip it. That was about that. That's what that. Right. Like he doesn't do that,
that obvious.
right? He still thinks it applies to them, that he records that, right? But so the idea that
that's what the fathers were saying was that, say, John had a vision of the donatists that wrote
this verse just for them in Africa is ridiculous, right? And that the verse has no other layers of me.
This is a contextualization, right? This is an application made by the fathers of the church to a
situation in the church in their day.
Right. There was this schism that happens in Africa of the Donutus. And the Donutus claim
that the salvific grace of God is confined to their churches in Africa. Right. And that
no one else has valid sacriots. No one else could be saved. Right. Except their churches
in Africa. And the church's brother say, ham. Right.
and point two first John two and make an argument.
A settlement for the whole world.
Yes.
Right.
And so, but that's just one contextualization.
That text can be recontextualized.
Right. That pattern can be re-instanced
in manifold different ways.
They're not going to be radically contradictory.
Right. But they're not going to be identical either.
because different areas of the church and different places are going to face different issues.
Right? They need to deal with, but they're all going to be dealing with them,
according to the truth that is Jesus Christ, according to the logos.
And so, there is this strange quest for contextlessness.
Yeah. This thing means that.
It may just be Plato brain. We're all looking for the ideal form.
We're all trying to get away from particularity and the material and the messiness of human life. We don't want that
We want extract ourselves from that, but that way lies nothingness. That's nihilism
Yeah, as we already said a person not related to anything is nothing
Has no identity
Right plate is men's in nihilism
So
The key thing here is there
is no system of interpretation or rules or processes that are free standing,
that are objective, that stand outside of reality against which you judge reality.
Hmm.
Right.
Against which you judge reality.
And so that means anyone who says anyone who makes a statement of meaning.
This verse means this, this quote from the saints means this.
this situation, what's going on in this situation means this, right?
They are doing the act of application.
Right.
Right. That is what they are doing.
And all such statements therefore are opinions.
Right. And, you know, opinion doesn't mean
not true or you know, like that's just your opinion man.
and it's
a ruling, right? Judges issue opinions and people don't, I mean, I'm sure maybe some people do
say to them, but people normally would not say to them, well, that's just your opinion, your honor.
I know this, this is the ruling. It's just your legal opinion. Yeah, right. Exactly. But the
thing that the issue is called an opinion, because it's there, this is their application of the law
of in this case, right? Right. Right. They're ruling, right? It's a opinion that sense. And therefore,
opinions issued by various people, right?
Here's how the canons ought to be applied in this instance.
Here's how the scripture ought to be applied in this instance.
Here's how whatever ought to be applied in this instance.
Right?
Whether that opinion, that ruling is worthwhile,
is something you should care about,
is something you should pay attention to.
It's purely based on the authority of the one opining.
Is this a person who God has entrusted with the authority
to issue these opinions and judgments or not?
Yeah, if the answer is no, then that is just your opinion man.
That is irrelevant.
Right.
I mean, right?
You can give it advice.
Right.
Like someone could give their opinion on my pending court case.
But unless there's a judge, it doesn't matter.
Right.
Yeah.
Like, it doesn't matter.
it matter. They're not the person who got as
put the position right with the authority to do that right to make that call to make that application in this instance
Right, and that's what all of these things are is they are the applications
taking the logos that is Christ right applying him ultimately right to
The various situations of the life of the church in our own life
Applying them in a way that gives them meaning
that allows them to be navigated.
And that ultimately leads us to salvation.
Yeah.
So to give some some final thoughts on this.
To me, a very fascinating and provocative conversation.
I've talked about this a couple of times before, but and so hopefully this won't be too redundant with other things have said.
said but within this context God willing it'll be it'll be
something usefully new. So, you know, I myself, by my personality, by my training, by my habits,
one of the things that I am is an antiquarian. I love old stuff. I love going to museums and seeing
old stuff perfectly preserved or restored or whatever. The idea that you would take
you know, an old painting and just change it because you think it would
better in some other way. That horrifies me as I hope it would most of us.
One of my favorite museums here in the US is the Cloisters which is in Northern
Manhattan, beautiful museum of medieval art. So therefore it's almost all Christian art.
And I think that the way that a lot of Orthodox Christians approach Orthodox
Christianity is an antiquarian way.
This is kind of a modernish idea that you take this thing from the past and you encase it in a display case.
And you look at it and that's the thing that it is.
Right? And we treat Orthodox Christianity that way a lot.
And people tend to pick some particular time or place or maybe some you know,
popery.
of times and places, bits that they like from various things. And for them, then they say,
this is orthodoxy. This is the thing. And then they judge what other people are doing according to
that. They judge often, maybe they're parish priest, they're bishop, right. It sometimes was said
about the Protestant Reformation, that in the Reformation, everyone is a priest except for priests.
And I think that this attitude for Orthodox Christianity is everyone is a bishop except for bishops
that the opinions of people on social media about various things are
given more weight
by by some people
than
the people whose job it is to actually take care of our churches
And I know that like it can be scary
free.
You know, what if it all goes wrong?
And I know that if father, this is part of what you're going to talk about.
So I don't want to get too deep into it.
Um, it's an important question, right?
What if bishops make the wrong decisions?
I understand America has found it on the idea that important people make the wrong
decision.
That's why we have a country.
Um, but what I will say is this on the on the positive side that as you look at
the history of the church.
It seems to me was always this assumption that the church continues to be alive and active
and that bishops have real authority in the moment to do their jobs, that the church can act
creatively in the moment to apply the life in Christ in that time, in that place, in
those particular situations.
is said to one person or one community may not be applicable to another person.
community or it may need to be said in a different way, right? And that life in Christ,
life in his body, the Orthodox Church, is not life in a museum. Now, I'm not saying that
as some kind of revolutionary, I am the opposite of revolutionary. Anyone's ever met me or read
anything I've ever written or listened to what I say knows that that is not my deal at all.
I didn't become
orthodox to make some improvements. There's nothing for me to improve. At the same time,
and this is not contradictory, we see that the church continues to function creatively.
New things are being said, which are consistent with all the old things. That's where it
goes off the rail, is if you say a new thing that's not consistent with the old things.
It is not the application of the same pattern which
is Christ, right? And so I think that, you know, we live in a world that's kind of messed up
these days, particularly. There's a lot of really strange
malays and pathologies that we're living in here now in 2023. And so I understand the response to
so that the feeling that the world is declining,
the feeling that, like wow, this...
This is the craziest things I've ever been.
And number one that's simply not true.
If you read the history of the world, there have been some way crazier times, way more
apocalyptic moments.
For some people, this is a very apocalyptic moment.
I mean, there are people living in places where their world is on fire.
So I get that.
Right?
I get that.
Um
But to me the response to that even like if let's say this is really it. This is really like this is
the true and the final end of the world is coming very very soon like within a year whatever five years,
10 years, 40 years, I don't know like let's go full how Lindsey say that's true. The response to that
is not to draw back and in case the Christian life.
and simply demand that everybody stare at this musying exhibit of Christianity.
The response of the Church has always had in various apocalyptic moments, in confronting
various anti-Christs, which St. John said had come, multiple in his time had come, and
more will come.
The response of the church is creativity.
Is building something.
new. Right? As things collapse around, the church builds something beautiful and new. Number
one, so the people who are running from the collapses have somewhere to go. But number two,
because our job is to participate in the Kingdom of Heaven, which is this building project.
We're supposed to be engaged in the building project. Right? And what's being built is not a big
fortress, what's being built is the New Jerusalem.
Right?
And so to me, that's not only a way more hopeful approach to societal collapse and decline,
on whatever level that's actually true.
I only see what I see, looks pretty messed up in many ways where I am.
But the truth is, is most of what I see that makes me think of collapse, is stuff I see
kind of out there.
Like my life, my actual life, like my town is not collapsing.
It's a good place to live.
God.
It's a good place to live, right?
I'm not saying other things aren't happening, but my life, that's the reality of my life.
God is blessing us at this moment and this place.
And that our task in the world is continued to, with confidence, because Christ is our
head.
You know, I think some time.
to move forward with confidence and to do this building.
I think sometimes people act, Christians act like atheists.
They act like God is not with us, despite that being one of his names.
Emmanuel, God with us, that he's not with us.
That like, it all depends on us.
So you had all better get it right.
You had all better be perfect and pure.
You would all better say the exact right things because if you don't dot,
Like have some
faith that God is here and is working and he's going to take care of stuff.
And even if someone gets deeply messed up and hurts a lot of people,
God is going to bring justice and vindication to that situation.
He will.
Maybe not on the timetable that I would prefer, probably not, but he will.
God has this.
And our response to that is not to either act like he doesn't have it or to sit back
and say, okay.
do everything of the Lord, but rather knowing that he has it then to function creatively within that.
Because that's what the church does. The church is alive. It's alive. It's not some moth with a
pinstuck through it, put up on the wall that everyone can admire and don't touch it. That's not
the churches so father
So, yeah, I'll go, I'll double down on the provocative.
Say, Silawon at one point says that if your spiritual father tells you to sin, you should
do it for your salvation.
He says that if your spiritual father tells you to do something.
And you do it out of obedience and it turns out that it was sin. God holds your spiritual
father accountable for that, not you. And your obedience can save your soul. The problem
is, the problem you have is that you sat there and you judged your spiritual father's
words. I'm trying to decide for yourself whether what he was telling you to do was right
or not.
That's the problem you have.
Not that he might have told you to do the wrong thing, which he might very well have.
Is there someone who is a spiritual father? I'm sure I get it wrong.
Sure I get it wrong sometimes at least sometime.
One of the
worst things that certain forms of Protestantism
Due to people.
is they set up this situation for a person.
By the way, I have some Protestant friends who think this is a feature not a book, so your
mileage may vary.
But to me, this seems like a heavy weight to get thrown out to a person.
An individual person, as a Christian, has to essentially sort of figure out Christianity
for themselves.
They are responsible to go and read the scriptures themselves, to read spiritual books, to decide
what they believe
leave and where they fall on all manner of theological issues and issues of church life.
I mean basic things.
Do you baptize babies or not?
How often do you celebrate the Eucharist?
What even is the Eucharist?
The Trinity.
How do you view the Trinity?
How do you view Jesus' humanity and divinity?
interpretation of all men or
you have to go and decide for yourself all of these things. And by the way, at least some of them,
if you get them wrong, you'll go to hell for eternity. That to me is a burden no human can really bear,
if they understand what's being asked of them. That's an unbearable burden. Nonetheless,
You don't have to go very far in the Orthodox world to encounter Orthodox Christians who
try to approach the Orthodox faith in the same way.
They think that what they are to do as an Orthodox Christian is to go and usually not
the Scriptures, to read church fathers and to read various books and decide where they
They stand on all of these issues and what the true orthodox position is on all of these
issues.
Because if you get any of them wrong, you're not really orthodox.
Therefore, probably not on the path to salvation.
If you could do that to yourself, right, my next suggest that Protestant services are much
shorter, they're scheduled more conveniently, and a lot of them you can drink coffee.
So why take all the bad parts and none of the good parts?
The Orthodox Church has done this great favor for you of having preserved the Christian
faith for 2000 years handed down from the apostles.
Of having this rich history of leaders appointed by God, God even appointed the bad ones, God
even appointed the heretics.
appointed by God who fallibly.
interpreted and applied the deposit of faith.
Fallibly interpreted and applied the scriptures.
Fallibly interpreted and applied the cannons.
All the way down to the present day.
So that you can now come and be a part of a community
that is working out its own salvation,
that is overseen by fallible leaders
who will be doing their fallible best.
Bring all of that to bear, which is ultimately the logos,
which is ultimately Christ himself.
Bring them to bear on your life.
and help you find salvation, so that you don't have to try to do this by yourself,
so that you don't have to make this high stakes wager on your own theological acumen,
so that you can follow rather than lead,
and be secure in that. This is a gift that the church gives you,
to be able to follow your spiritual father in his guy.
So, not have to do what is right in your own eyes and hope that it's end is not destruction
contra the Scriptures.
To do rather what is right of the eyes of the authority that God has established and put
over you.
Now, I'm not saying this because I'm a priest and I don't want people to criticize me.
Please criticize me.
I enjoy it.
Because number one, nothing you could possibly say about me publicly is...
half as bad as the truth. And number two, I really do find it sickly entertaining when people say outlandish
Negative things about me. So criticize me to the hill. I don't care. That's not that
right
And you certainly don't have to look very hard to find
Bishops misbehaving in all manner of ways making bad decisions, right again
Everybody's fallible. I'm not I'm not apologizing for anybody
Right.
But I'm talking to you.
Right. I'm talking to you as a person.
Person is trying to become a human person who's trying to figure out what their life means.
It's trying to become like Christ.
You got to test the spirits.
The spirit that wants you to decide what real orthodoxy is and then compare your priest and your bishop to it.
Is that spirit leading you to become a fully participant part
of your community and find salvation,
or is it pulling you away from that?
Then you know what kind of spirit that is.
Does it matter how it presents itself?
Does it matter if it wears a classic?
Does it matter if it claims to be
from the Holy Mountain or heaven itself, right?
That's not the spirit that's leading you to salvation.
Right.
Spirit that's leading you to salvation is the Holy Spirit.
It's leading you to become part of a community, to discover there who you are, and how you're
late to the other people in God's world and to God's world itself, and how you as a
person can become like Christ and figure out what it all means.
Amen.
Amen. Amen.
Well, that is our show for tonight.
Thank you very much everyone for listening.
If you didn't get through to us live this time, we'd still like to hear from you.
You can email us at LordOfSpirit.AncientFate.com.
You can message us at our Facebook page or you can leave us a voice mill at SpeakPipe.com
slash LordOfSpiritz.
And if you have basic questions about Orthodox Christianity or need help finding a parish,
head to Orthodoxintro.org.
And join us for our live broadcasts on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at
7 PM Eastern 4 PM Pacific, where we'll ask
Why are we here? What's life all about? Is God really real or is there some doubt?
Well tonight we're going to sort it all out.
If you're on face meeting of life.
You can follow our page and join our discussion group,
leave reviews and ratings in all the appropriate places,
but most importantly, please share this show with a friend who is going to benefit from it.
Finally, be sure to go to www.aggetfade.com.stokes.org
to help make sure we and lots of other AFR podcasters stay on the air.
What is life? What is our fate? Is there a heaven or hell?
Do we reincarnate? Is mankind evolving?
or is it too late? Well, tonight here's the meaning of life.
Thank you, good night. God bless you all.
You've been listening to The Lord of Spirits
with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick,
and Father Stephen De Young, a listener-supported presentation
of ancient faith radio.
And I beheld, and I heard the voice of many angels
round about the throne, and the beasts, and the elders,
and the number of them was ten-
thousand times ten thousand and thousands of thousands,
saying with a loud voice worthy as the land
that was slain to receive power and riches
and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.
Glory to Jesus Christ, glory forever,
you're listening to ancient.
Jesus drew near to the boat, walking on the water.
It was the fourth watch of the night, meaning that it was the darkest hour.
The disciples quivered with fear at the uncanny sight.
The Water.